"Blocking the Cancer Metastasis Enzyme
MMP-9 with Beans and Chickpeas"
Although we’re spending
billions of dollars
on fancy new types of chemotherapy,
the overflowing sink that is
cancer treatment is expected
to rise by about 70 percent
over the next two decades
because drugs are being used
to merely mop up the mess
rather than turn off the faucet.
You can’t really give drugs
to people to prevent cancer
because of the side effects and
cost, but there is said to be
overwhelming evidence that
the dietary bioactive compounds
found in whole plant-based
foods have signiﬁcant
anticancer and cancer
preventive properties.
In a previous video, I talked
about the impact of diet
and nutrition on the
ten hallmarks of cancer.
The bottom line is that evidence
points to a diet with minimal
animal products, and perhaps more
importantly, maximal plant foods.
Some foods that appear to be
particularly beneficial include fruit
(especially berries), a variety
of vegetables (especially greens),
legumes (which are beans, split
peas, chickpeas, and lentils),
nuts and seeds (especially
flaxseeds), mushrooms, onions,
garlic, herbs and spices
(for example, turmeric),
and, as a beverage, green tea.
Chemotherapy may
not even be particularly
good at mopping up the mess.
Cancer drugs often impair
quality of life and fail to extend
patient survival.
Let me say that again.
You’re paying for drugs, maybe
selling your house to pay for drugs,
that may just be making
your life worse for no benefit.
Some have suggested we demand
at least three months of extended
life from pharmaceuticals,
but if we demand
that chemo actually works,
might they give up altogether?
On the other hand, maybe by
mandating clinically important
benefits—what a concept—
maybe big pharma would reallocate
resources towards targeting
the more critical cancer processes
like metastatic spread,
because it’s the tumor metastasis
that accounts for 90 percent
of cancer-related deaths.
Who cares if some drug
shrinks your primary tumor if
it’s spreading and cutting
your life just as short?
What about controlling metastatic
cancer with some of those
natural bioactive
compounds in plants?
Evidently it has been proven that
plant phytochemicals are able
to inhibit nearly every step of the
invasion through metastasis cascade,
at least in vitro, in a petri dish.
Here’s a list of some
purported dietary sources of
antimetastatic phytochemicals,
all shown to block all sorts of
cancer signaling pathways,
but let me focus on one:
matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs).
Since about 90 percent of cancer
disability and death is due
to cancer spreading, metastasis,
let’s talk about these MMPs
which actively participate
in the whole metastatic journey.
Matrix metalloproteinases are
enzymes that allow the cancer
to tunnel through the
surrounding flesh and invade the
lymph or blood vessels
and then enable it
to burrow in and grow
somewhere else.
So, Big Pharma developed matrix
metalloproteinase inhibitor drugs,
which worked great in animal
models but caused severe
side effects when
they tried them on humans.
So, what about using food?
There are special proteins in
legumes that reduce MMP activity.
What else might you
expect from a Dr. Lima?
But which is the leading legume?
Researchers tested eight
different kinds: lupin beans,
chickpeas, split peas,
black-eyed peas, lentils, and
more common beans (like
kidney, black, or pinto),
fava beans, and soybeans.
Which do you think worked best?
Without any beans, the matrix
metalloproteinase activity
churned away at around 100 percent
and dripping on some protein
from pea soup-type peas
didn’t seem to help much,
but the black-eyed peas, lentils,
common beans, and fava beans
cut enzyme activity by
more than 50 percent.
Guess what slashed activity
by more than 90 percent?
Lupin beans, chickpeas, and soybeans.
Yeah, but does this translate into
slowing down the cancer’s spread?
Researchers plated a layer
of human colon cancer cells
in a petri dish and then
took a razor blade to clear
a strip down the middle.
Within 48 hours, the cancer
quickly converged to fill the gap.
But when a little protein
from lupin beans, chickpeas,
or soybeans was dripped on,
it looks like the cancer cells
struggled to close the distance.
Okay, but they used raw beans.
You don’t know if these anti-
cancer proteins are destroyed
by cooking until you put it to the test.
And the matrix metalloproteinase
inhibitors in soybeans at least,
remain active after cooking.
So, maybe it’s no wonder that
dietary legume consumption
reduces risk of colorectal
cancer. Yeah, but colon cancer,
which sprouts from the
inner lining of the colon,
could potentially come in contact
with some of these bean proteins.
Presumably they wouldn’t
get into the bloodstream.
Those eating vegetarian do
seem to have significantly
lower levels of matrix
metalloproteinases, but this is just
thought to be due to their
lower levels of inflammation,
similar to the way non-smokers
also have lower MMP levels.
This is good, because this
enzyme isn’t just a cancer biomarker,
but also may be involved
in autoimmune diseases
and cardiovascular disease.
The machete-type nature of
this enzyme can hack through
the inflamed cholesterol-filled
atherosclerotic lesions
lining diseased arteries and
cause the plaque to rupture.
People know that those eating
more plant-based tend to have
less heart disease but
may not realize they harbor
significantly less cancer risk too,
particularly among those eating
strictly plant-based diets.